<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blog</title><link>https://nicolezok.com/</link><description>Recent content on Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 08:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://nicolezok.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>I think maybe the introvert/extrovert scale is bad</title><link>https://nicolezok.com/posts/i-think-maybe-the-introvert-extrovert-scale-is-bad/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicolezok.com/posts/i-think-maybe-the-introvert-extrovert-scale-is-bad/</guid><description>A hypothesis: When people talk about introversion/extroversion, they&amp;rsquo;re not using those terms to refer to specific/consistent things, and having access to these terms prevents people from thinking about and understanding what they&amp;rsquo;re actually experiencing.
Some things I might mean when I say I&amp;rsquo;m introverted, e.g. as an explanation for why I don&amp;rsquo;t want to go to a party:
When I go to parties I often end up making small talk with a lot of people, and I find that less satisfying than having a deep conversation with one or two people I expect that the group of people at this party will be either people I don&amp;rsquo;t know very well or don&amp;rsquo;t like very much, so I don&amp;rsquo;t expect it to be fulfilling to spend time talking with them It&amp;rsquo;s not really clear what activity you&amp;rsquo;re supposed to do when you go to a party, and it would be effortful to figure it out I&amp;rsquo;m feeling emotionally depleted for some unrelated reason and as a result I don&amp;rsquo;t have very much energy left to spend on socializing I have a general lack of self-confidence and worry about making a good impression on people, which makes it hard to relax and have a good time I have social anxiety (this could also mean a variety of things, including some of the points above) If I forget about the concepts of introversion and extroversion, I have an opportunity to learn more about myself and get more value out of my experiences.</description></item><item><title>an unmet need</title><link>https://nicolezok.com/posts/an-unmet-need/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2021 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicolezok.com/posts/an-unmet-need/</guid><description>It turns out I have way too high a bar for actually posting, so here&amp;rsquo;s a small anecdote from today.
I was with a friend and we were in transition between two activities. I noticed I felt like I needed something before we started the next activity, but wasn&amp;rsquo;t immediately sure what it was, so I said &amp;ldquo;I HAVE AN UNMET NEED.&amp;rdquo; Friend laughed, I spent 30 seconds figuring out what my unmet need was (I was cold) and how to fix it (make tea).</description></item><item><title>Some relationship models, how they interact, and my best guesses at what to do about the problems they're pointing at</title><link>https://nicolezok.com/posts/some-relationship-models-how-they-interact-and-my-best-guesses-at-what-to-do-about-the-problems-they-re-pointing-at/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicolezok.com/posts/some-relationship-models-how-they-interact-and-my-best-guesses-at-what-to-do-about-the-problems-they-re-pointing-at/</guid><description>For the past year or so, Kyle and I have been doing an in-depth study of relationships (and ours in particular), with a goal of enabling us to have the best relationship we can have with each other. We also wanted to get a better grasp on what marriage is for and do a deep gut check that we actually want to marry each other (spoiler: we do!).
I started out by looking for books that would teach me about how great relationships work, and had a hard time finding the information I wanted.</description></item><item><title>Hello world!</title><link>https://nicolezok.com/posts/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 07:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://nicolezok.com/posts/hello-world/</guid><description>Hey world,
As you can tell, I&amp;rsquo;ve created a blog. My immediate reason for doing this is because I&amp;rsquo;ve been studying relationships (and marriage in particular) for the past year or so, and wanted to have a place to share what I&amp;rsquo;ve been learning about that. I expect having a blog will also have the benefit of helping me think more clearly by forcing me to write things down. I think this is enough of a starting point, so we&amp;rsquo;ll see where it goes :)</description></item></channel></rss>